Leah: For a product to be successfully used,
a good ‘user interface’ [UI] is critical.
Users won’t stay long and will quickly stop
using a product such as a website or app
if they are having a bad user experience.
When users leave a site quickly this is
known as having a ‘high bounce rate’.
Bad UI design could also result in security issues,
data integrity, and affect the performance of a website.
Chris: One of the main overarching considerations when
creating, is to put the user at the heart of the design.
For the user to have a good experience, the UI designer
will need to focus on certain elements, such as:
• Placing users in control of the interface
• Making it comfortable to interact with
• Reducing the cognitive load
• Making user interfaces consistent
Leah: so, what exactly are the Principles of UI design
When it comes to user interface [UI] design
there are certain characteristics to consider:
• Clarity – All UI element need to be clear
for users to interpretate correctly.
Users should not need to decode a particular meaning
of an element such as interactive and navigation items.
• Chris: Consistency –The UI design needs to consistent
such as the branding colours and typography.
This is so users can recognise ways to use
elements such as the placement and colour of a
button or menu item is always the same colour,
size, font and positioned in the same place.
• Leah: Ease of use – also categorised as user control – the
interface needs to be intuitive and minimises confusion
such as using simple navigation, providing feedback [such
as a ‘success’ message], and using clear labels for buttons.
• Chris: Comfort – also categorised as Familiarity
this links to clarity and ease of use.
The UI should allow for previous experiences of the
users, use simple language, include inclusivity, and
be designed for responsiveness for use on different
items such as a mobile phone, tablet or laptop.
• Leah: Tolerance – also categorised as Forgiveness
– Users needs to be forgiven of their mistakes that
they make especially when first using the interface.
• Chris: Efficiency – the interface should plan
for minimal input and provide shortcuts for
experienced users so they can be more productive.
• Leah: Accessibility – this is linked to the
Comfort principle as it is key that user
feel comfortable and in control when using a
product, no matter what their requirements are.
UI design needs to take motor, cognitive,
hearing, or visual impairments into consideration.
Chris: Other ‘Principle’ terms that may be used could
include Structure, Simplicity, Visibility, and Feedback.
This would depend on the type of interface that is
going to be designed, and the strategy, processes,
or practices of the company or organisation.